{"tossups": [{"question": "This composer incorporated the song \"Bright Sun, You Do Not Shine Equally\" into a piece to raise money for Red Cross agents helping Serbian casualties of an 1876 war with Turkey, his <em>Marche Slave</em>. For 10 points, name this Russian composer who depicted the Battle of Borodino turning back Napoleon from Moscow in his <em>1812 Overture</em>.", "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich <b><u>Tchaikovsky</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A Confederacy of thirteen of these places included eight \u201ccity\u201d ones and five \u201cforest\u201d ones. Several of these places fought in the Kappel Wars, and the westernmost ones have been French-speaking for centuries. These places include Uri and Glarus, while in Graubunden, Romansh and German are spoken. For 10 points, name these geographical divisions that make up Switzerland.", "answer": "<b><u>canton</u></b>s of Switzerland", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man depicted Leutze\u2019s (<b>LOYT-zuh\u2019s</b>) <em>Washington Crossing the Delaware</em> in the background of a satirical portrait of three old women intended to be crossdressed depictions of the Founding Fathers. A painting by this artist shows his dentist and sister as a farming couple.  For 10 points, name this Midwestern artist of <em>Daughters of Revolution</em> & <em>American Gothic</em>.", "answer": "Grant <b><u>Wood</u></b> [Grant DeVolson <b><u>Wood</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A leader of this country's Communist Party wrote the <em>Prison Notebooks</em> and coined the concept of \"hegemony.\" This country was also home to the man whose <em>On Crimes and</em> <em>Punishments</em> founded the field of criminology, and the coiner of the 80-20 rule. For 10 points, name this homeland of Antonio Gramsci (<b>GROM-shee</b>) and Vilfredo Pareto.", "answer": "<b><u>Italy</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "This man replaced Robert M. La Follette, Jr. in the Senate after a primary campaign in which he accused La Follette of war profiteering. This man was the subject of the \"Declaration of Conscience Speech\" and Joseph Welch's remark that he had \"no sense of decency.\" For 10 points, name this Wisconsin Senator who worked with Roy Cohn to find Communists.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>McCarthy</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The first four holders of this title were called \"rightly-guided\", or <em>rashidun</em>. Two claimants to this title fought at Karbala. A research center called the House of Wisdom was built under a holder of this title named Harun al-Rashid, who ruled from Baghdad. For 10 points, name this Islamic title used by the Umayyads and Abbasids, which means \"successor to the Prophet.\"", "answer": "<b><u>caliph</u></b>s [or <b><u>khalifah</u></b>; or <b><u>khalifa</u></b>t rasul Allah]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "A writer from this country denounced a war as \"a fight between two bald men over a comb\" in the poem <em>Juan L\u00f3pez y</em> (wahn loh-pez ee)<em> John Ward</em> and described the endless \"Library of Babel.\"For 10 points, name this home country of Jorge Luis Borges (<b>BORE-hays</b>), who condemned its participation in the Falklands War.", "answer": "<b><u>Argentina</u></b> [or <b><u>Argentine Republic</u></b>; or Republica <b><u>Argentina</u></b>]", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "One holder of this position was assassinated after going to a railway station to meet Vladimir Kokovstov in retaliation for signing the Eulsa Treaty. Another holder of this position earned the nickname \u201cRazor\u201d while heading the military police in the Kwantung Army, and attempted suicide while awaiting trial before the Tokyo War Crimes Tribunal. For 10 points, name this government position held by Ito Hirobumi and Hideki Tojo.", "answer": "<b><u>Prime Minister</u></b> of <b><u>Japan</u></b> [accept equivalents]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Fulk III of Anjou built dozens of a type of this structure called a donjon. An early version of this structure featured a motte (<b>MAHT</b>) and a bailey. One type of entrance to these structures was the barbican, which often included a portcullis. These structures centered on a keep and were surrounded by moats. For 10 points, name this type of fortification common in Medieval Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>castle</u></b>s [prompt on more general answers involving \"fortification\"]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This law's enforceability was upheld in the Supreme Court case of <em>Ableman v. Booth</em>, which invalided the \"personal liberty laws\" many states passed to undermine it. This law led to a contentious trial in Boston over Anthony Burns. For 10 points, name this portion of the Compromise of 1850 which required northern free states to help recapture escaped slaves.", "answer": "<b><u>Fugitive Slave</u></b> Act  <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 2 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This animal is believed to give the \"five products\" including gobar, an energy source. The tilak mark is often made from the excrement of these animals, which are the subject of the holiday Gopastami. Killing these animals was prohibited by the Vedas, and they are now a major cause of traffic hindrance in Delhi. For 10 points, name these animals sacred to Hindus.", "answer": "<b><u>cow</u></b>s [or <b><u>cattle</u></b>, etc.]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This man responded to Barack Obama's Cairo address with the 2009 \"Bar-Ilan (<b>BAR ee-LAHN</b>) speech.\" He originally became prime minister after defeating Shimon Peres in a 1996 direct election, and has been in office again since forming a coalition against Tzipi Livni's Kadima (<b>kah-DEE-muh</b>) party. For 10 points, name this current prime minister of Israel.", "answer": "Benjamin \"Bibi\" <b><u>Netanyahu</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "One of these particles was posited by Sheldon Glashow to solve the Cabibo theory. The discoverer of these particles named them after a nonsense word in <em>Finnegans Wake</em> and developed the SU(3) system for classifying them, which he called the Eightfold Way. For 10 points, name these building blocks of subatomic particles, discovered by Murray Gell-Mann.", "answer": "<b><u>quark</u></b>s", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "A comic book series starring this character is where The Punisher first appeared. In the 1970s, this character was tormented by The Jackal creating clones of his loved ones, which provided the basis for a reviled 1990s \"Clone Saga\" storyline. For 10 points, name this Marvel character who opposes Dr. Octopus, The Lizard, and Venom and is the alter-ego of Peter Parker.", "answer": "<b><u>Spider-Man</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This character's British counterpart was a real person named Ruby Loftus, and her Canadian version was Ronnie the Bren Gun Girl. This character is distinct from the subject of the Howard Miller \"We Can Do It!\" poster, and was popularized by a Norman Rockwell painting. For 10 points, name this World War II poster character who promoted women's working in factories.", "answer": "<b><u>Rosie the Riveter</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "James Carleton launched a \"total war\" against this tribe, which was forced onto the \"Long Walk to Bosque Redondo\" by Kit Carson. In November 2014, this tribe's member Chester Nez died; Nez was the last surviving member of this tribe who worked as a \"code talker\" during World War II. For 10 points, name this large American Indian tribe in the Southwest.", "answer": "<b><u>Navajo</u></b> [or <b><u>Dine</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Nancy Lopez was one of the most dominant athletes in this sport during the 1980\u2019s, while former track star Babe Didrickson Zaharias also won numerous tournaments in this sport in the 1950\u2019s. Se Ri Pak of South Korea achieved success in this sport at a young age, as did Michelle Wie, who competed in a series of events on the PGA tour. For 10 points, name this sport in which Annika S\u00f6renstam made history in 2001 by shooting 59 in a competition round.", "answer": "<b><u>golf</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "The Brezhnev Doctrine was used to justify the invasion that ended this period of time. It began with its creator announcing \u201csocialism with a human face.\u201d Gust\u00e1v Hus\u00e1k replaced the leader who began this period, Alexander Dub\u010dek (<b>DOOB-check</b>), after the Warsaw Pact invasion deposed him. For 10 points, name this relaxing of one-party control in Czechoslovakia in 1968.", "answer": "<b><u>Prague Spring</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This editor of the newspaper</u> </b><em><b><u>Iskra</u></b></em><b><u> wrote about the \u201cburning questions of our</u></b> <b><u>movement\u201d in a pamphlet titled</u> </b><em><b><u>What Is to Be Done?</u></b></em><b><u> As leader, he instituted the moderate</u></b> <b><u>New Economic Policy. He issued a series of (+)</u> \u201cApril Theses\u201d after riding through Germany on a sealed train. This man, for whom (*)</b> St. Petersburg was renamed in 1924, brought his country out of World War I with the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk. For 10 points, name this leader of the Bolsheviks.", "answer": "Vladimir <b><u>Lenin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A holder of this office feuded with a faction led by his rival Milo and engineered the exile</u></b> <b><u>of his enemy Cicero. Another holder of this office proposed the reforming Lex Sempronia</u></b> <b><u>Agraria and, like his brother, was killed by an Optimate (+)</u> mob. Publius Clodius Plucher and Gaius and Tiberius Gracchus all held this position, which was granted (*)</b> sacrosanctity and the power of the <em>intercessio</em>, or the veto. For 10 points, name this office of the Roman Republic, created to represent the plebeians.", "answer": "<b><u>tribune</u></b>s [or <b><u>tribune</u></b> of the plebeians; or <b><u>tribunus</u></b> plebis; or <b><u>tribune</u></b> of the plebs; do not accept \u201cmilitary tribune\u201d]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's campaign commercials, which were designed by Richard Wirthlin, included</u></b> <b><u>the \"bear in the woods ad\" advocating military preparedness. He asked \"are you better off</u></b> <b><u>now than you were four years ago?\" when he won the Presidency and was re-elected on the</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> \"Morning in America\" campaign. This supporter of the Strategic Defense Initiative defeated (*)</b> Walter Mondale by a landslide in 1984. For 10 points, name this Republican President of the 1980s.", "answer": "Ronald Wilson <b><u>Reagan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An object aboard this vessel includes Blind Willie Johnson's recording of \"Dark Was the</u></b> <b><u>Night, Cold Was the Ground\" and the first Brandenburg Concerto, as well as greetings in</u></b> <b><u>fifty-five languages. This vessel, which holds a (+)</u> \"golden record\" compiled by Carl Sagan, was launched in 1977 and left the (*)</b> solar system in 2013. For 10 points, name this probe which is currently the farthest manmade object from Earth.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Voyager</u></b> 1</em>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "<b><u>Governor William Lane forced the negotiation of this event, which was the high-water</u></b> <b><u>mark for William Marcy and other proponents of a southern route for the (+)</u></b> <b>Transcontinental Railroad. This event resulted in a ten million dollar price being paid for the Mesilla Valley area. This event was negotiated by the American ambassador to (*) </b>Mexico, with Santa Anna. For 10 points, name this this 1853 land transfer of parts of Arizona and New Mexico to the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Gadsden Purchase</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This program had a complex system of over three \"work classifications\" and targeted</u></b> <b><u>those with educational problems; eighty-nine percent of its participants had not graduated</u></b> <b><u>high school. This program, directed by Robert Fechner, sent the Indian Division to work</u></b> <b><u>on (+)</u> soil projects. This program employed three million people and planted three (*) </b>billion trees from 1933 to 1942. For 10 points, name this New Deal program in which men lived in camps and worked outdoors.", "answer": "<b><u>CCC</u></b> [<b><u>Civilian Conservation Corps</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This European power used the \"ten-cow rule\" to distinguish and privilege some colonial</u></b> <b><u>subjects. The Casement Report criticized the colonial policies of this European power,</u></b> <b><u>alleging that it cut the (+)</u> hands off unproductive rubber workers. This European power treated the Tutsis better than the Hutus in what became Rwanda, and ran a so-called (*) </b>\"Free State\" exploited by King Leopold II. For 10 points, name this European country which colonized most of the Congo.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Belgium</u></b> [or <b><u>Belgi\u00eb</u></b>; or <b><u>Belgique</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man wrote about the execution of John Brown in \u201cThe Portent,\u201d the first poem in</u></b> <b><u>his unpopular collection</u> </b><em><b><u>Battle-Pieces</u></b></em><b><u>, and described his visit to the Middle East in</u> </b><em><b><u>Clarel</u></b></em><b><u>.</u></b> <b><u>He described fraudsters on the Mississippi River in</u> </b><em><b><u>The</u> </b></em><b><u>(+)</u></b> <em><b>Confidence Man</b></em><b>, and created the characters of Stubb, Flask, and (*) </b>Starbuck in another novel. For 10 points, name this American author of nautical tales such as \u201cBilly-Budd\u201d and a novel set on the <em>Pequod</em>, <em>Moby-Dick</em>.", "answer": "Herman <b><u>Melville</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}